and the economic model that you and I
والنموذج الاقتصادي
did business in,
الذي مارسنا فيه الأعمال،
and, in fact, continue to do business in,
وفي الواقع، لازلنا نمارس في ظله الأعمال،
was built around what probably Milton Friedman
أسس حول ما حدده ميلتون فريدمان
put more succinctly.
بإيجاز كبير.
And Adam Smith, of course, the father of modern economics
وكذلك آدم سميث، الأب الروحي للاقتصاد الحديث
actually said many, many years ago,
الذي قال الكثير، منذ سنوات عديدة،
the invisible hand,
اليد الخفية
which is, "If you continue to operate
التي تعني ، "إذا استمريت في العمل
in your own self-interest
لمصلحتك الخاصة
you will do the best good for society."
قد تنجز الأفضل لمجتمعك ".
Now, capitalism has done a lot of good things
حاليا، لقد حققت الرأسمالية الكثير من الأشياء الجيدة
and I've talked about a lot of good things that have happened,
ولقد تحدثت عن الكثير منهـا والتي حدثت،
but equally, it has not been able to meet up
لكنها، عجزت على مجابهة
with some of the challenges that we've seen
بعض التحديات التي رأيناها
in society.
في المجتمع.
The model that at least I was brought up in
النموذج الذي على الأقل ترعرعت في ظله
and a lot of us doing business were brought up in
والكثير من الذين يمارسون الأعمال قد ترعرعوا في ظله
was one which talked about
و الذي تحدث عنه
what I call the three G's of growth:
هو النموذج الذي أسميه بـثلاثي النمو:
growth that is consistent,
نمو منتظم،
quarter on quarter;
من سنة الى أخرى؛
growth that is competitive,
ونمو قادر على المنافسة،
better than the other person;
لتكون الأفضل بين الجميع؛
and growth that is profitable,
ونمو يؤدي الى الربح،
so you continue to make
حتى يمكنك الاستمرار في تحقيق
more and more shareholder value.
المزيد من الربح للمستثمرين.
And I'm afraid this is not going to be good enough
وأخشى ألا يكون هذا النموذج كافيا
and we have to move from this 3G model
وسيكون من الواجب علينا الانتقال من نموذج ثلاثي النمو
to a model of what I call
إلى النموذج الذي أسميه
the fourth G:
رباعي النمو
the G of growth that is responsible.
العنصر الرابع في النمو المسئول
And it is this that has to become
والذي يجب أن يصبح
a very important part
الجزء المهم جداً
of creating value.
لخلق قيمة مضافة.
Of not just creating economic value
ليس فقط خلق القيمة الاقتصادية
but creating social value.
ولكن خلق القيمة الاجتماعية.
And companies that will thrive are those
والشركات التي ستزدهر هي تلك
that will actually embrace the fourth G.
التي ستتبنى بالفعل نموذج رباعي النمو.
And the model of 4G is quite simple:
ونموذج رباعي النمو بسيط للغاية:
Companies cannot afford to be just innocent bystanders
لن تبق الشركات مجرد متفرجين
in what's happening around in society.
في ما يحدث حولها في المجتمع.
They have to begin to play their role
بل يجب عليها البدء في القيام بدورها
in terms of serving the communities
المتمثل في خدمة المجتمعات المحلية
which actually sustain them.
ومساندتها .
And we have to move to a model
ولابد أن ننتقل إلى نموذج
of an and/and model which is
النموذج الذي
how do we make money and do good?
يمكننا من كسب المال وفعل الخير؟
How do we make sure
كيف يمكننا التأكد
that we have a great business
أن لدينا أعمالا عظيمة
but we also have a great environment around us?
وكذلك بيئة عظيمة حولنا؟
And that model
وكل مايهتم به هذا النموذج
is all about doing well and doing good.
هو فعل الخير وكذلك فعله بإحسان.
But the question is easier said than done.
ولكن القول دائما أسهل من الفعل.
But how do we actually get that done?
ولكن كيف يمكننا فعلا القيام بهذا؟
And I do believe
أعتقد
that the answer to that is going to be leadership.
أن الإجابة على ذلك سوف تكون القيادة.
It is going to be to redefine
هو إعادة تحديد
the new business models
النماذج الجديدة للأعمال
which understand
هذا يعني
that the only license to operate
أن الترخيص الوحيد للعمل
is to combine these things.
سيكون الجمع بين هذه الأمور.
And for that you need businesses
ولهذا نحن بحاجة لشركات
that can actually define their role
التي يمكنها في الواقع تحديد دورها
in society
في المجتمع
in terms of a much larger purpose
فيما يخص غايتها
than the products and brands that they sell.
أكثر من المنتجات والعلامات التجارية التي يسوقونها.
And companies that actually define a true north,
والشركات التي تقوم بتحديد ،
things that are nonnegotiable
الأشياء الغير قابلة للتفاوض
whether times are good, bad, ugly --
مهما كانت الأوقات جيدة، سيئة، أو قبيحة-
doesn't matter.
هذا لا يهم.
There are things that you stand for.
وهناك الأشياء التي تدعمها.
Values and purpose are going to be the two
القيم والأهداف مقبلة على أن
drivers of software
تشكل البرامج
that are going to create
التي تؤدي الى خلق
the companies of tomorrow.
شركات الغد.
And I'm going to now shift
سأنتقل الآن الى
to talking a little bit about my own experiences.
التحدث قليلاً عن تجربتي الخاصة.
I joined Unilever in 1976
انضممت إلى شركة يونيليفر في عام 1976
as a management trainee in India.
كمتدرب إدارة في الهند.
And on my first day of work
وفي أول يوم لي في العمل
I walked in and my boss tells me,
بينما كنت أشتغل قال لي رئيسي،
"Do you know why you're here?"
"هل تعرف لماذا أنت هنا؟"
I said, "I'm here to sell a lot of soap."
أجبت ، "أنا هنا لأبيع الكثير من الصابون".
And he said, "No, you're here to change lives."
وقال، "لا، أنت هنا لتغيير حياة الناس."
You're here to change lives.
أنت هنا لتغيير حياة الناس
You know, I thought it was rather facetious.
أ تدرون، أعتقدت أنها كانت مجرد مزحة.
We are a company that sells soap and soup.
نحن شركة تبيع الصابون.
What are we doing about changing lives?
كيف لنا أن نغير حياة الناس؟
And it's then I realized
ومن ثم أدركت
that simple acts
أنه بـعمل بسيط
like selling a bar of soap
كبيع قطعة صابون
can save more lives
يمكن أن تنقذ الكثير من الأرواح
than pharmaceutical companies.
من شركات الأدوية.
I don't know how many of you know
لا أعلم كم منكم يعرف
that five million children don't reach the age of five
أن 5 ملايين من الأطفال لا يبلغون سن الخامسة
because of simple infections that can be prevented
بسبب التهابات بسيطة يمكن الوقاية منها
by an act of washing their hands with soap.
بمجرد غسل أيديهم بالماء والصابون.
We run the largest
نحن الان نشتغل على أكبر
hand-washing program
برنامج لغسل اليدين
in the world.
في العالم.
We are running a program on hygiene and health
أننا نعمل على برنامج عن النظافة والصحة
that now touches half a billion people.
والذي يمس نصف بليون نسمة.
It's not about selling soap,
ليس الأمر مجرد بيع للصابون،
there is a larger purpose out there.
هناك غاية كبرى من وراء ذلك.
And brands indeed can be
وفي الواقع يمكن أن تكون العلامات التجارية
at the forefront of social change.
في طليعة التغيير الاجتماعي.
And the reason for that is,
والسبب في ذلك،
when two billion people use your brands
عندما يستخدم 2 بلیون من الناس العلامات التجارية الخاصة بك
that's the amplifier.
ان هذا شيء عظيم .
Small actions can make a big difference.
الأعمال البسيطة يمكن أن تخلق فرقا كبيرا.
Take another example,
سأعطيكم مثال آخر،
I was walking around in one of our villages in India.
كنت أتجول في إحدى القرى في الهند.
Now those of you who have done this
أولئك الذين قاموا بذلك من قبل
will realize that this is no walk in the park.
سيدركون أن هذا ليس تجوالا في الحديقة.
And we had this lady
كانت لدينا هذه السيدة
who was one of our small distributors --
وكانت إحدى موزعينا الصغار
beautiful, very, very modest, her home --
جميلة، متواضعة جداً، -
and she was out there,
كانت هناك،
dressed nicely,
بلباس أنيق،
her husband in the back, her mother-in-law behind
من ورائها زوجها وحماتها
and her sister-in-law behind her.
وشقيقة زوجها .
The social order was changing
إن النظام الاجتماعي في تغير
because this lady
بفضل هذه السيدة
is part of our Project Shakti
التي تعتبر جزء من " مشروع شاكتي "
that is actually teaching women
في الواقع إنها تعمل على تعليم المرأة
how to do small business
كيفية القيام بالأعمال التجارية الصغيرة
and how to carry the message
وكيفية إيصال رسالة
of nutrition and hygiene.
الاعتناء بـالتغذية والنظافة.
We have 60,000 such women
حاليا، لدينا 000 ،60 امرأة من هذا القبيل
now in India.
في الهند.
It's not about selling soap,
ليس الأمر مجرد بيع للصابون،
it's about making sure
بل التأكد
that in the process of doing so
انه بـالقيام بذلك
you can change people's lives.
يمكنك تغيير حياة الناس.
Small actions, big difference.
الأعمال الصغيرة، فرق كبير.
Our R&amp;D folks
لا يعمل فريق البحث العلمي الخاص بنا
but they're working to make sure we use less water.
بل أنهم يعملون أيضا للتأكد من أننا نستخدم كميات أقل من المياه.
A product that we've just launched recently,
منتج قمنا بإطلاقه مؤخرا،
One Rinse product that allows you to save water
منتج تنظيف يسمح لك بـتوفير الماء
every time you wash your clothes.
في كل مرة تغسل ملابسك.
And if we can convert all our users to using this,
لو استطعنا اقناع جميع المستعملين بـاستخدام هذا المنتج،
that's 500 billion liters of water.
سنوفر 500 بلیون لتر من الماء.
By the way, that's equivalent to one month of water
على فكرة، هذا يعادل شهرا واحداً من المياه
for a whole huge continent.
لقارة كاملة ضخمة.
So just think about it.
لذا فكروا فقط في الأمر.
There are small actions that can make a big difference.
هناك أعمال بسيطة يمكنها أن تحدث فرقا كبيرا.
And I can go on and on.
ويمكنني الاستمرار.
Our food chain, our brilliant products --
صناعتنا الغذائية، ومنتجاتنا الرائعة-
and I'm sorry I'm giving you a word from the sponsors --
أنا آسف سأشير الى أسماء بعض الرعاة -
Knorr, Hellman's and all those wonderful products.
كنور، هيلمان، وجميع هذه المنتجات الرائعة.
We are committed to making sure that
اننا ملتزمون بالتأكد من أن
all our agricultural raw materials
كل المواد االزراعية
are sourced from sustainable sources,
تأتي من مصادر مستدامة،
100-percent sustainable sources.
100 في المئة من مصادر مستدامة.
We were the first
وكنا أول
to say we are going to buy all of our palm oil
من قال أننا سنشتري كل ما نحتاجه من زيت النخيل
from sustainable sources.
من مصادر مستدامة.
I don't know how many of you know that palm oil,
وأنا لا أعلم كم منكم يعرف أن عدم شراء زيت النخيل
and not buying it from sustainable sources,
من مصادر مستدامة،
can create deforestation that is responsible
يمكن أن يؤدي الى إزالة الغابات، المسؤولة عن
for 20 percent of the greenhouse gasses in the world.
20 في المائة من الغازات المسببة للاحتباس الحراري في العالم.
We were the first to embrace that,
كنا أول من تبنى ذلك،
and it's all because we market soap and soup.
وكل ذلك بـسبب أننا نسوق الصابون.
And the point I'm making here
وما أريد أن أوضحه هنا
is that companies like yours, companies like mine
أن الشركات مثل شركتي، أو مثل شركاتكم
have to define a purpose
يجب أن تحدد هدفا
which embraces responsibility
والذي يشمل المسؤولية
and understands that we have to play our part
وفهم أنه يتعين علينا أن نقوم بـدورنا
in the communities in which we operate.
في المجتمعات التي نعمل فيها.
We introduced something called
لقد قدمنا ما يسمى
The Unilever Sustainable Living Plan, which said,
خطة يونيليفر للعيش المستدام، تحت شعار،
"Our purpose is to make sustainable living commonplace,
"هدفنا جعل العيش المستدام أمرا مألوفاً،
and we are gong to change the lives
وسنغير حياة
of one billion people over 2020."
1 بلیون من الناس في أفق 2020 ".
Now the question here is,
والسؤال هنا، الآن
where do we go from here?
الى أين نحن ذاهبون؟
And the answer to that is very simple:
والجواب على ذلك بسيط جداً:
We're not going to change the world alone.
لن نغير العالم لوحدنا.
There are plenty of you and plenty of us
هناك الكثير منكم والكثير منا
who understand this.
والذين يفهمون هذا.
The question is,
والسؤال:
we need partnerships, we need coalitions
نحن بحاجة إلى شراكات، و إلى تحالفات
and importantly, we need that leadership
والأهم من ذلك، نحن بحاجة إلى القيادة
that will allow us to take this from here
التي ستسمح لنا بالشروع في هذا انطلاقا من هنا
and to be the change
لنكون التغيير
that we want to see around us.
الذي نريد أن نراه حولنا.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)